A Guide to the Photographs, Series 1011-1081 FA438
Rockefeller Archive Center
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA), 1946-1968, n.d.; 1027; 6.2 Cubic Feet 19 boxes.
  - Chile, 3
    - Plan Victoria, Gardening, Prints: 15 (Box 6, Folder 140)
      274. No caption. 275. No caption. 276. No caption. 277. No caption. 278. Huerto "Las Lilas". 279. No caption. 280. El seor Andrade plantando un rbol. 281. No caption. 282. Rosario school. 283. No caption. 284. Escuela Rosario, March 1966. 285. No caption. 286. No caption. 287. No caption. 288. No caption.
    - Plan Victoria, Miscellaneous, Prints: 46 (Box 6, Folder 141)
      289. - 299. No caption. 300. Construccin Escuela "Las Lilas". 301. No caption. 302. Danceat Las Lilas by Indian members of the community. 303. John Camp and Jim Hyde at the community of Las Lilas. 304. - 317. No caption. 318. Typical recognition plaque. 319. The Chilean countryside in the Department of Victoria, Province of Malleco - Scene of the "Plan Victoria." 320. - 333. Captions included with photographs. 334. No caption.
    - Plan Victoria, Reports, 1963, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 142)
      "Rural Education Program - Chile: Victoria, Province of Malleco, May 1963."
      "American International Association for Economic and Social Development: Report on Rural Education Program in Chile known as the 'Plan Victoria," March 1964."
  - Venezuela, 4
    - CADA, General, Prints: 14 (Box 7, Folder 143)
      1. CADA manager, Antonio B. Toro (right) explains how fruit and vegetables are kept fresh in cooled compartments at Minimax. 2. CADA truck loads at company warehouse at Puerto La Cruz for delivery to local retail markets. 3. 60,000 sq. ft. prefabricated building mounted by VBEC at La Arreaga district of Maracaibo houses both CADA warehouse and new milk pasteurization plant. 4. Buyers look over stock at CADA warehouse in Puerto La Cruz. 5. Typical corner grocery in Caracas contrasts sharply with modern food stores opened by CADA. 6. Cia. Anon. Distribuidora de Alimentos, Venezuela, June 1949. The 65,000 sq. ft. warehouse being constructed by the CADA subsidiary company, in south Caracas' busy industrial and commercial district will be completed in November. The construction of adequate warehouses in large marketing centers in Venezuela is part of the CADA program to stimulate the production and conservation of foodstuffs, which are often lost through spoilage at present. At least twenty percent of warehouse space, one third of which is equipped with cold storage facilities, will be made available to individual Venezuelan farmers and merchants on a rental lease basis. 7. Modern food warehouse being constructed for use by CADA in Caracas' busy industrial district, San Martin, will be terminated in November. 8. Modern food warehouse being constructed for use by CADA in Caracas' busy industrial district, San Martin, will be terminated in November. 9. Memo: Preliminary plans for Todos supermarket in Caracas on Avenida de las Mercedes. (Not for release). 10. Clearing field for warehouse - now owned by Ven. govt. 11. Clearing field for warehouse - now owned by Ven. govt. 12. No caption. 13. No caption. 14. No caption.
    - CADA, MiniMax, Prints: 36 (Box 7, Folder 144)
      15. CADA, Venezuela. 6/1949. MiniMax market opened in busy south Caracas trade intersection on May 2, 1949. 16. MiniMax opened for business on May 2, 1949. 17. Dr. Saverio Barbarito (right), President of the Corpoacion Venezolana de Fomento, and Pedro Mancera (left), member of the Corp. board of directors, discuss milk sales with CADA manager, Antonio Toro, at the MiniMax market. 18. CADA manager, Antonio Toro, shows Dr. Saverio Barbarito (center), President of the Corporacion de Fomento, and Mr. Pedro Mancera (left), member of the Corp. board of directors, PACA chickens on sale at MiniMax market. 19. CADA. MiniMax "superette" in Caracas demonstrates efficient utilization of space in small market for customer convenience and adequate display of a wide variety of foods. May 1949. 20. R.O. Provost, manager of the Retail Foods Division of the VBEC, talks business with William F. Coles, President of the Board of Directors of Automercado, SA. 21. CADA, Venezuela. 5/1949. Fruits and vegetables are kept fresh in cooled compartments at MiniMax. 22. CADA, Venezuela. 5/1949. MiniMax boosts Venezuelan canned goods such as Pampero products in effort to stimulate national food industry. 23. CADA, 6/1949. customers take quickly to convenient self-service system at MiniMax. 24. CADA, Prices are marked on all articles sold at MiniMax, outdating local practice of grocery store haggling. 25. MiniMax, first of series of retail food establishments to be built by CADA is an effort to modernize food merchandising in VE and effect more equitable distribution of basic foods to the public. 26. MiniMax market, the first of a series of modern food establishments to be constructed by CADA, will open under VE ownership on May 3. The 132 sq. meter store, located in the busy "La Bandera" district of Caracas, is equipped with modern food retailing facilities and will be operated according to the latest merchandising practices including self-service system. 27. View from the interior of the MiniMax market in the La Bandera section of Caracas reveals a busy commercial area and poor residential districts clustered on neighboring hillsides. The market is the first of a series of retail food establishments to be constructed by CADA in an effort to modernize food merchandizing in VE and effect more equitable distribution of basic foods to the public. The store will open under the VE company "Abastos Gaber, SA" on May 3. 28. CADA trains MiniMax employees to dispatch large numbers of customers efficiently, promptly, and courteously. 29. CADA technician Albert Bildner (left) emphasizes modern food retailing practices at MiniMax. 30. MiniMax, Valencia, VE. Soda fountain in new MiniMax store in Valencia is an added attraction for shoppers. 31. MiniMax offers from 100 to 380 more items then other retail outlets in the area, in an effort to provide the public with a complete line of foods and small household articles under one roof, thus facilitating shopping. 32. MiniMax uses modern refrigeration equipment and emphasizes cleanliness in food handling. 33. Attractive displays distinguish "vitamin row", the vegetable section of the supermarket MiniMax in Valencia, state of Carabobo, and her sister supermarket, TODOS of Maracaibo, state of Zulia. Here a clerk freshens up the beets while a woman shopper, her basket partly filled, pauses to investigate and item opposite. 34. The MiniMax soda fountain at Valencia was inaugurated 9/19/53 with society belles of the Carabobo capital treating the trade to cups of Pepsi-Cola squirted from the shiny, new taps. The soda fountain was added just three years and a month after VBEC's second supermarket and Valencia's first went into business. 35. INLACA dairy products are sold through the soda fountain at MiniMax in Valencia. 36. Pepsi-cola on the house brought a flock of customers to the new MiniMax soda fountain. The soda fountain - TODOS of Maracaibo also installed one this year, proved a solid success, not only providing a restful interlude for busy, thirsty shoppers, but a chance for a quick lunch for working people in the district. 37. Garden stuff, fresh and dewy, is a standard attraction, appetizingly "doubled" by mirrors at MiniMax. 38. Valencia shoppers like the MiniMax system of marking prices on all items, a practice seldom followed in Venezuela grocery stores. 39. MiniMax offers from 100 to 380 more items then other retail outlets in the area, in an effort to provide the public with a complete line of foods and small household articles under one roof, thus facilitating shopping. 40. MiniMax hit the society pages when four debutantes passed out free pop to the crowd on inaugural day for the new soda fountain. Business has continued brisk at the long refreshment counter, which occupies the corner nearest the entrance of the supermarket. TODOS of Maracaibo, VBEC's first supermarket - MiniMax is the second - also has installed a soda fountain. 41. New MiniMax store in Valencia is third of a group of modern retail food stores developed by CADA to apply latest principles of food merchandising. 42. Valencia shoppers take quickly to self-service system introduced to that city by the new MiniMax supermarket. 43. The MiniMax supermarket in Valencia, owned by a subsidiary of VBEC, matches its modern exterior in its use of the latest technical devices in retail food handling. 44. The MiniMax supermarket in Valencia, owned by a subsidiary of VBEC, matches its modern exterior in its use of the latest technical devices in retail food handling. 45. Valencia's first supermarket, MiniMax, was opened by CADA August 18th, on the busy corner of Urdaneta Plaza and Bolivar Ave. Its location makes its price advantages and shopping conveniences available to some 40,000 inhabitants which make up the San Jose commercial and residential district. 46. MiniMax offers from 100 to 380 more items then other retail outlets in the area, in an effort to provide the public with a complete line of foods and small household articles under one roof, thus facilitating shopping. 47. MiniMax, VBEC's second supermarket, went into business in the heart of downtown Valencia in August of 1950. A true test of the supermarket in Venezuela, MiniMax serves an exclusively Venezuelan public and is so located that the clients represent a cross section of all economic classes in the Carabobo capital, Venezuelan fourth city. An urban landmark the "perros calientes" (hot dogs) wagon - is parked in front of the store. 48. MiniMax, VBEC's second supermarket, went into business in the heart of downtown Valencia in August of 1950. A true test of the supermarket in Venezuela, MiniMax serves an exclusively Venezuelan public and is so located that the clients represent a cross section of all economic classes in the Carabobo capital, Venezuelan fourth city. An urban landmark the "perros calientes" (hot dogs) wagon - is parked in front of the store. 49. MiniMax store recently opened in Valencia is another step forward in the rapid modernization taking place in Valencia and Carabobo State; spproximately fifty per cent of the foods sold at this new market are local produce, especially from the Carabobo region. 50. Dr. Anoldo Gabaldon (center) and Dr. Arturo Luis Berti (right), owners of the Venezuelan grocery enterprise, "Abastos Gaber, SA", sign retail franchise agreement under which they will operate the MiniMax food store in the "La Bandera" district of Caracas. The market is the first of a series to be constructed by CADA, and operated by Venezuelan grocers in an effort to modernize retail food merchandising in Venezuela and effect a more equitable distribution of basic foods to the public. Mr. AB Toro, Manager CADA, can be seen at left.
    - CADA, TODOS, Prints: 16 (Box 7, Folder 145)
      51. CADA. TODOS, a modern self-service supermarket, is operated by a VBEC subsidiary in Maracaibo, VE's second largest city. 52. A large variety of fresh produce, grown in the rich agricultural region of Zulia, is sold through the TODOS supermarket in Maracaibo. 53. CADA. TODOS, a modern self-service supermarket, is operated by a VBEC subsidiary in Maracaibo, VE's second largest city. 54. Customers take quickly to self-service in food store, TODOS, opened by VBEC in collaboration with Venezuelan capital in Maracaibo, rapidly-expanding capital of VE's western oil boom area. 55. TODOS, a modern self-service supermarket, is operated by a VBEC subsidiary in Maracaibo, VE's second largest city. 56. Late shoppers find it cool and convenient to visit the TODOS shopping center. On Saturday the shops remain open until 9pm. 57. Late shoppers find it cool and convenient to visit the TODOS shopping center. On Saturday the shops remain open until 9pm. 58. In Maracaibo, Venezuela's second largest city, a VBEC subsidiary operates CA TODOS, a modern US type supermarket which carries food and household articles. 59. In Maracaibo, Venezuela's second largest city, a VBEC subsidiary operates CA TODOS, a modern US type supermarket which carries food and household articles. 60. R to L: Diego Garcia, VE instructor in TODOS and Pres. Of the Board of Directors; Frank J, Rothaug, Member of Board of Directors; RO Provost, Manager of TODOS retail store, with experience in wholesale and retail food business in both the United States and Mexico, and James O'Neil, Assistant Manager of retail store. 61. TODOS, a modern self-service supermarket, is operated by a VBEC subsidiary in Maracaibo, VE's second largest city. 62. TODOS, a modern self-service supermarket, is operated by a VBEC subsidiary in Maracaibo, VE's second largest city. 63. TODOS food store offers Maracaibo public complete line of foodstuffs and small household articles under one roof, allowing one-stop marketing. Other conveniences of the new store are self-service, display of prices, arrangements for easy, rapid shopping, and pre-cooled produce, which, familiar to housewives in the US, are innovations to many VE buyers. 64. No caption. 65. No caption. 66. No caption.
    - CIDEA, Administration, Prints: 35 (Box 7, Folder 146)
      1. Signing of new three year contract between the Venezuelan government and the American International Association to extend nutrition information program of CIDEA to July, 1954. Standing, left to right: Dr. Alfonso Rodrigues, legal consultant of AIA, Dr. Cesar Quiroz, legal consultant of Ministry of Public Health, Health Minister Raul Soules Baldo and John R. Camp, director of AIA in Venezuela. Seated, Dr. A. Gonzalez Puccini, director of Instituto Nacional de Nutricion, signing contract for Venezuelan government. 2. Dr. A. Gonzalez Puccini, Director General of the National Nutrition Institute, presenting first prize to Manuel Rodriguez Cardenas of "El Nacional", Caracas, for best newspaper article on National Nutrition Day. 3. Executive Board of CIDEA holds first meeting. Venezuelan board members, l. to r., Dr. A. Valero Hostos of Ministry of Education, Profesor Juan Jose Pacheco, director of Venezuelan public schools for Ministry of Education, Dr. Demetrio Castillo, chief of Sanitation Education of Ministry of Health, Dr. Jose Ignacio Baldo, chief of division of tuberculosis of Ministry of Health, and Dr. A. Gonzalez Puccini, President of the Board and Director of Venezuelan National Nutrition Institute. 4. With a graphic display of CIDEA nutrition information activities as background, Dr. Armando Gonzales Puccini, President of the Executive Committee, invites representatives of the Ministries of Health, Education and Agriculture to study the CIDEA experimental Centers at San Casimiro and Cantaura with a view self perpetuation. Seated at Dr. Gonzales' left is Dr. Demetrio Castillo health, and Chairman of the Study Commission. 5. See back of photo. 6. See back of photo. 7. No caption. 8. No caption. 9. No caption. 10. See back of photo. 11. See back of photo. 12. See back of photo. 13. See back of photo. 14. Signing agreements for programs of international cooperation sponsored jointly by the American International Association and the government of Venezuela. Right to left: Dr. Amando Gonzalez Puccini, Director of the National Nutrition Institute of Venezuela; Dr. Raul Soules Baldo, Venezuelan Minister of Health and Social Welfare; John R. Camp, Director of A.I.A in Venezuela; Dr. Cesar Quiros, Juridical Counselor of the Venezuelan Ministry of Health; Dr. Alfonso Rodriguez, A.I.A. August 28 1951. 15. Signing of agreements for programs of international cooperation sponsored jointly by the American International Association and the government of Venezuela. Right to left: John R. Camp, Director of A.I.A. in Venezuela; Dr. Pedro Jose Lara Pena, Venezuelan Minister of Agriculture; Dr. Eduardo Ibarra Ruiz, Director of Agriculture of the Venezuelan Ministry of Agriculture. August 28, 1951 16. See back of photo. 17. See back of photo. 18. Signing of agreements for programs of international cooperation sponsored jointly by the American International Association and the government of Venezuela. Right to left: John R. Camp, Director of A.I.A in Venezuela; Dr. Pedro Jose Lara Pena, Venezuelan Minister of Agriculture; Dr. Eduardo Ibarra Ruiz, Director of Agriculture of the Venezuelan Ministry of Agriculture; Dr. Antonio J. Betancourt, Section Chief in the Office of Agricultural Economy, Ministry of Agriculture. August 28, 1951 19. Signing of agreements for program of international cooperation sponsored jointly by the American International Association and the Venezuelan government. Seated: Dr. Raul Soules Baldo, Venezuelan Minister of Health and Social Welfare. Standing: (Right to Left) Dr. Amando Gonzalez Puccini, Director of the National Nutrition Institute of Venezuela; Dr. Quiros, Juridical Counselor of the Venezuelan Ministry of Health; Dr. Alfonso Rodriguez, A.I.A. August 28, 1951. 20. Signing of agreements for programs of international cooperation sponsored jointly by the American International Association and the government of Venezuela. Right to left: John R. Camp, Director of A.I.A. in Venezuela; Dr. Raul Soules Baldo, Venezuelan Minister of Health and Social Welfare; Dr. Amando Gonzalez Puccini, Director of the National Nutrition Institute of Venezuela; Dr. Cesar Quiros, Juridical Counselor of the Venezuelan Ministry of Health; Dr. Alfonso Rodriguez, A.I.A August 28 1951. 21. Signing of agreements for program of international cooperation sponsored jointly by the American International Association and the Venezuelan government. Right to left: Dr. Pedro Jose Lara Pena, Venezuelan Minister of Agriculture; John R. Camp, Director of A.I.A. in Venezuela; Dr. Antonio J. Betancourt, Section Chief of Agricultural Economy Division of the Venezuelan Ministry of Agriculture: Dr. Eduardo Ibarra Ruiz, Director of Agriculture of the Venezuelan Ministry of Agriculture. August 28 1951 22. BELLA VISTA MARKET, CARACAS-Officials of CIDEA headed by Dr. Rangel Lamus, Minister of Agriculture (right center), are photographed as they observe the facts of a cooperative CIDEA- MAC Program of informing early morning marketers about basic nutrition facts while they purchase their week's supply of food. Others in the picture are left to right, Sr. Juan Pable Conde, Director of Mercados Libres, Sra. Stella Vasquez, Cidea Dietitian and Nutrition Information Specialist, and Dr. Pausolino Lopez Cardenas, Jefe de Division de Distribucion de Economia Agricola. 23. BELLA VISTA MARKET, CARACAS-The Minister of Agriculture, Dr. Rangel Lamus, looks over some of the CIDEA literature and graphics distributed by Nutrition Specialist, Hilda Vasquez, left, and other CIDEA officials at the opening of the new Mercado Libre at Bella Vista. Looking on is Dr. Daniel Uzcategui Ramirez, Director de Economia Agricola, who worked directly with CIDEA to develop patterns of cooperation whereby people purchasing their supply of foods at the Mercados Libres in Venezuela will at the same time receive basic information concerning the nutritional values of foods. 24. Edward Stuntz, Director of C.I.D.E.A., discusses plans for the San Casimiro program with Venezuelan Ministry of Health officials in Maracay. Left to right are: Dr. Jose Maria Bengoa, of the National Public Nutrition Institute; Dr. Armando Castillo Plaza, Director of the Aragua State Sanitary Zone; Dr. Rodrigo Varo, Sub-Director of the Zone; Edward Stuntz; and Dr. Bernal Jimenez, San Casimiro doctor. 25. C.I.D.E.A Director, A. Edward Stuntz (center) tours San Casimiro's hillside farms and visits rural families in an effort to fit the program of the local Center into the everyday problems of the community. Accompanying him is Dr. Jose Maria Bengoa (right), of the National Nutrition Institute; Dr. Bernal Jimenez (left), San Casimiro's rural doctor; and two of the town's citizens who were cooperating with the C.I.D.E.A. activities. 26. Left to Right: Edward Stuntz, Director of C.I.D.E.A; Napoleon Arriaz, Sportswriter "El Nacional"; Elba Arriaz, C.I.D.E.A., seated: Carmen Guevara Partidas "Dona Barabara" 27. No caption. 28. No caption. 29. No caption. 30. Venezuela's Minister of Public Health, Dr. Raul Soules Baldo, gives interview for CIDEA press service to Martin R. Reynolds, director of CIDEA, and Raul Torres Gamez, chief of press service. 31. November 18, 1951. Minister of Public Health, Raul Souls Bald addressing school groups on Nutrition Day. 32. November 18, 1951. Dr. Gonzalez Puccini, Director of Instituto Nacional de Nutricion; Dr. Raul Souls Bald, Minister of Public Health, and Dr. Simon Beccera, Minister of Education at Nutrition Day festivities, Teatro Nacional. 33. Cabinet ministers cooperate in CIDEA radio campaign. Minister of Agriculture Pedro Jose Lara Pena records a greeting to farmers throughout Venezuela on the occasion of National Nutrition Day, November 18, 1951. 34. Dr. Simon Becerra, Minister of Education, in Nutrition Day address at Teatro Nacional, Caracas, Venezuela, November 18, 1951. 35. No caption.
    - CIDEA, Agriculture, Prints: 1 (Box 7, Folder 147)
      36. New pig pen completed.
    - CIDEA, CIDEA Presentation, Prints: 6 (Box 7, Folder 148)
      37. CIDEA staff workers and representatives of the Caracas press, discuss the graphic presentation of the CIDEA program at the Centro Venezolano Americano. 38. The nutrition demonstration-information community centers of Sam Casimiro and Cantaura are explained in detail by Mrs. Stella Marietta, Supervisor (standing right) to technicians of the Venezuelan Ministries of Health, Agriculture and Education. 39. CIDEA's nutrition education program in the schools of Venezuela is explained to Venezuelan Government representatives by Dr. Bartolome Oliver, professor of the University of Caracas and CIDEA education consultant. Through school clubs and regular nutrition classes and exercises CIDEA takes knowledge of balanced diet to the nation's young. 40. A. Edward Stuntz, director, uses graphic presentations of the twelve CIDEA nutrition information and education projects, to define and describe the complete program to representatives of the Venezuelan Government. 41. The idea of CIDEA as a processing machine for scientific facts on food and nutrition for the ultimate information of the Venezuelan citizen is explained to news men by CIDEA director Stuntz. 42. News writers and nutritionists show, interest in the media corner of CIDEA's graphic display of its national nutrition information program.
    - CIDEA, Educational Films, Prints: 79 (Box 7, Folder 149)